e.j. sahala (they/them)

SF Bay Area, or Remote +1.408.218.2006

cv@saha.la

in https://www.linkedin/in/ejsdotsh https://github.com/ejsdotsh

★ https://ejs.sh

Visionary, seasoned technologist with 24 years of experience in the design, build, and operation of backbone, campus, cloud, and datacenter networks that are automated, scalable, reliable, and secure. Network engineer and architect, systems builder, and autodidactic polymath with extensive experience leading the research and development, and (novel) application of technology, to build collaborative solutions to large-scale and service provider infrastructure performance, provisioning, monitoring, reliability, and deployment problems.

Key Results

improved performance and reliability – reduced technical debt – improved operational efficiencies legacy technology integration – strategic corporate impact – standardization and compliance improved process, training, and documentation – reduced toil – decreased costs

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Adobe

Senior Cloud Network Reliability Engineer - 2021.09-2022.12

Provided technical leadership to the global team to engineer solutions for network automation, implementation, monitoring, and operations.

- Championed initiatives to add more rigor to network engineering practices, including design and operability reviews, blameless post-mortems, automation and standardization, and decision-making process improvements
- · Developed tooling to integrate with legacy applications, automate manual processes, and standardize configurations
- Researched infrastructure, negotiated contracts, and partnered with vendors to complete capacity, hardware, and software upgrades required to provide secure and reliable connectivity for high-profile executive video presentations, company events, and return-to-office mandates

Box

Senior Network Engineer - 2019.11-2021.08

Network design, build, automation, and operation of a global hyperscale network; responsible for everything from the top-of-rack to the network edge.

- Completed major hardware replacement and software upgrade projects; significantly improved customer experience, network capacity, and reliability
- Created/updated/maintained dashboards and documentation in Confluence, Jira, and Splunk to improve executive visibility of team projects and network status
- Rebuilt and maintained automation tooling to streamline network configuration and operation; reduced technical debt, improved standardization, and reduced deployment times from hours to minutes
- · Partnered with NRE and SRE to improve monitoring and observability with Sensu, PagerDuty, LibreNMS, Splunk

HERE Technologies

Principal Network Engineer - 2018.08-2019.10

Definition and continuous development of the architecture and design of the HERE global on-premise and cloud networks, supporting specialized mapping technologies, location data and related automotive services, for both individuals and companies, worldwide.

- Created and maintained standards and automation; introduced Ansible and developed integrations with legacy tools and data-sources, improving compliance, standardization, and reducing deployment times from hours to minutes
- Led global network QoS evaluation; identified and resolved multiple long-standing software bugs and policy inefficiencies, reducing packet loss and improving throughput 5-10x globally
- Led evaluation and rewrite of job descriptions, levels and responsibilities, and interviewing processes for the global network and infrastructure teams
- · Created, updated, and maintained onboarding, process, and standards documentation in Confluence and SharePoint
- Edge network redesign; hybrid multi-cloud interconnection and inter-VPC/VPN routing, virtualized edge/network services (FW, LB, DNS, HTTP, VPN), increased capacity

Gaikai/Sony

Senior Network Engineer - 2017.01-2018.05

Defined architectural requirements, acceptance criteria, and led hardware, software, and vendor evaluations for PlayStation Now's low latency, high availability, global gaming network.

- Developed and implemented documentation, process, and training improvements; improved operational efficiency, reduced deployment times by 10%
- Routing redesign reduced inter-regional latency by 5ms

Microsoft

Senior Engineer - Network Strategy & Planning - 2014.03-2017.01

Defined, developed, and documented technical strategies, standards, and policies, built stakeholder relationships and strategic partnerships, influenced contract negotiations, and managed capacity with infrastructure operators globally to support network growth and performance improvements.

- Led global network performance improvement program, collaborated with service owners to create documentation, define SLAs/KPIs and change processes, and direct implementation of network, software, and telemetry changes; reduced external CDN spend, reduced global service latencies, improved observability, and completed training and hand-over to Network Operations, reducing ticket triage time from 5+ days to <2 hours
- Partnered with O365 and Field Services to create and improve internal and customer-facing training, documentation, design standards, and best practices; greatly reduced service activation time, improved service stability and performance, and significantly improved customer experience, retention, and satisfaction
- Education, outreach, and peering and capacity negotiations at events and conferences (NANOG, RIPE, PTC, GPF);
 elected to DE-CIX Customer Advisory Board

Juniper Networks

Systems (Sales) Engineer - 2012.5-2013.8

Involved with all aspects of pre/post-sales; developed consultative relationships with technical and executive decision makers, responded to RFI/RFPs, and created and delivered training and documentation on product and service roadmaps, competitive research, best practices, and security alerts.

- Managed RMAs, feature requests, and bug scrubs
- Key team contributor in transforming resistance into success to exceed quota, and deliver over \$40-million in sales revenue

Infocrossing/Wipro
Intelepeer
Yahoo!
Alcatel-Lucent NZ
twtelecom
Terremark
Fusiontel
USA.net

Various

Network Architect/Staff Engineer - 2010.7-2012.5
Principal IP (Network) Engineer - 2009.3-2010.6
Tech Lead - Senior Network Engineer - 2007.5-2009.2
Principal Engineer - 2006.8-2007.5
Lead IP Network Engineer - 2005.6-2006.7
Lead Network Engineer - 2004.1-2005.1
Senior IP Engineer - 2002.9-2004.1
Network Engineer - 2001.3-2002.5
NOC Technician - 1999.9-2001.1

United States Marine Corps Reserve

Radio Operator

- Secret Clearance
- Meritorious promotions

Lance Corporal - 1998-2002

CORE SKILLS

learning and teaching – writing for technical and non-technical audiences – requirements gathering cross-functional consensus building – collaborative problem solving – automation & tooling technology strategy & standards development – architecture reviews & system design – needs analysis coaching & mentoring – contract negotiation & vendor management – process improvement

SELECT PROJECTS

CS Autodidact Documenting my self-education journey in Computer Science

https://github.com/ejsdotsh/cs-autodidact

YACHT My recursively named theme for the Hugo static site generator

https://github.com/ejsdotsh/yacht-hugo-theme

CERTIFICATIONS & AFFILIATIONS

Member, NANOG	2012-Present
Board Member, Customer Advisory Board, DE-CIX	2014-2016
Vice President, Colorado Chapter of the Internet Society (COISOC)	2011-2016
Steering Committee Member, Rocky Mountain IPv6 Task Force (RMv6TF)	2011-2016
Juniper Networks Certified Internet Specialist (JNCIS-ENT)	2012-2015
Juniper Networks Certified Internet Specialist (JNCIS-M)	2006-2009
Cisco Certified Network Professional (CCNP)	2002-2008

EDUCATION

Associate of Arts, Physics

Miami-Dade College